Guide to the J. Burke Knapp papers, 1960s
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
J. Burke Knapp papers
1960s
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
J. Burke Knapp
C0199
3.45 linear ft.; 7 boxes
Collection containes materials relating to various financial matters of the Arena Stage during the 1960s.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Arena Stage in 2000.
Historical Information
Arena Stage was an early leader in the resident theater movement. One of the first not-for-profit theaters in the United States as well as a pioneer of the regional theater movement the Arena Stage was the first regional theater to transfer a production to Broadway, the first invited by the U.S. State Department to tour behind the Iron Curtain and the first to receive a Tony Award. Co-founded in 1950 by Edward Mangum a teacher from the George Washington University, and Zelda Fichandler one of his students, Arena Stage was opened in Washington D.C. to fill the void left by the closing of the National Theater in 1948. Deriving it's name from the idea of "theater in the round," Arena Stage became one of the first resident theaters in the United States, beginning with a company of only eight actors. Today, Arena performs to over 250,000 patrons during a September to June season and employs nearly 200 theater professionals and craftpersons, who are responsible for all the costumes and scenery seen on stage. Many now- famous actors took part in Arena Stage productions during the early part of their careers. Some of them include Robert Prosky, Morgan Freeman, Dianne Weist, James Earl Jones, Kevin Kline, Christopher Guest, Yeardly Smith and Samuel L. Jackson.
Mr. J Burke Knapp was an Economist for the Federal Reserve Board, 1940-44; adviser on German economic affairs, U.S. Department of State and German Military Government, 1944-45; special assistant to the chairman, Federal Reserve Board, 1945-48; director, Office of Financial and Development Policy, Department of State, 1948-49; economic adviser U.S. delegation to NATO, 1950-51; U.S. president of the Joint Brazil-U.S. Economic Development Commission, 1951-52; and assistant director, economics department, International Bank for Reconstruction and Development, 1950-52, director, Western Hemisphere department, 1952-56, vice president, IBRD, 1956 and President of the Washington Drama Society.
Scope and Content
Collection containes materials relating to various financial matters of the Arena Stage during the 1960s.
Arrangement
Organized by subject.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives holds the Arena Stage records.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Arena Stage (Organization: Washington, D.C.)
Subjects:
Theater--Washington (D.C.)
Contents List
- J. Burke Knapp papers
  - Washington Drama Society, Inc. "Friends of Arena Stage" (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Washington Drama Society, Inc. "foundation" (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Washington Drama Society, Inc. correspondence (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Washington Drama Society, Inc. third class postage (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Washington Drama Society, Inc. construction contract (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Washington Drama Society, Inc. D.C. Sales tax exemption (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Washington Drama Society, Inc. D.C. personal Property Exemption (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Washington Drama Society, Inc. mortgage (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Washington Drama Society, Inc. correspondence (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Washington Drama Society, Inc. fichandler contract (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - accounts book (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Arena Enterprises Inc. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Arena Enterprises; Stock Agreement Form (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - incomplete dissolution of Arena Enterprises Inc. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - correspondence; Arena Enterprise Stock (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Trustee minutes and Stockholder minutes (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - correspondence and Joint Stock (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Arena Enterprises stock sale (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Washington Drama Society organization (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Arena Enterprises fiscal Summary (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Personal Arena Stage 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - personal Arena Stage 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - lease agreement with the District of Columbia, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Arena Stage II materials (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1956-1966 season summary sheet (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1966-1967 season summary sheets (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - misc. records (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1967-1968 season summary sheets (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Washington Drama Society Inc. trust indenture 1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Washington Drama Society Inc. trust indenture 1962 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - stock ledger book, bank notes and statements (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Washington Drama Society land lease with the District of Columbia (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - instruction form for disposition of stockholder assets memorandom on dissolution, 1959 (1 of 3) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - instruction form for disposition of stockholder assets memorandom on dissolution, 1959 (2 of 3) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - instruction form for disposition of stockholder assets memorandom on dissolution, 1959 (3 of 3) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Arena Stage II (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1959 appeal for nonprofit status (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - nonprofit application (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1968-1969 season summary sheet (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - misc. financial documents (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Arena Stage II (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - misc. correspondence (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - misc. correspondence (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - personal and property tax exemption information (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Washington Drama Society Inc. exemption application (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Washington Drama Society Inc. application for tax exemptions (Box 7, Folder 7)